<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Howe Howleglas deseyued a wynedrawer in Lubeke]</title>
            <title>Till Eulenspiegel. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1519</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10563</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853085</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 39:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Howe Howleglas deseyued a wynedrawer in Lubeke]</title>
                  <title>Till Eulenspiegel. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8+] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. van Doesborch,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1519?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Title from beneath woodcut on I4 recto.</note>
                  <note>Twenty-eight lines to the page, no catchwords.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment of eight leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:18451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>¶ Howe Howleglas de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eyued a wyne drawer in Iubeke.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18451:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> On a tyme ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Howlegias to Iubeke whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is very ſtrayght Iuſtyce And whyle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Howleglas was there abydynge he harde tell of a wyne drawer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was in a Iordes ſeller that was very prowde and preſumtyouſe and ſayd that there was no man that culde deſeyue hym or paſſe hym in wyſdome and there was none of all the lordes that loued hym Than thought howleglas in his mynde howe he myght deſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hym Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon a tyme toke Howleglas. ij. pottes one of water and the other empty and he hyd the empty pot that noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſawe it and cam to the ſeller and gaue the wyne dramer the emp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty pot and bad hym fyll the pot with wyne and ſo he dyd and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was full he browght it vp to Howleglas and than he loked a ſyde and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane whyle howleglas ſet the pot of water in the pot or wynes place and hyd the pot of wyne &amp; than aſhyd he the drawer what he ſhulde pay and the drawer ſayd. x. wytten that ſayd howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas the wyne is to dere for me / For I haue but viij. wytten Than was the wyne drawer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerye and ſayde wyll ye ſet another pryce on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyne than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes haue ſet Than ſayd howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas I haue no more money and I ſhall nath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it ſo tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take your wyne ageyne for I knewe it nat before / Than was the wyne deawer very angery and toke the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ot with the water &amp; bare
<pb facs="tcp:18451:2"/>it downe into the ſeller and pored out the water into the veſſell &amp; went it had ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyne &amp; cam and gaue Howleglas the pot and ſayd make ye me fyll wyne and ye haue no money to pay for it ye wene I be a fole &amp; than ſayde Howleglas pe be begyled of a fole and with that worde we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his waye with the pottes / and than the drawer myſtruſtynge Howleglas for the wordes that he ſayde and toke a ſergant and ouer toke hym and ſerched hym and than they founde that he had two pottes vnder his mantell tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toke they Howleglas &amp; peched hym for a thefe &amp; browght hym to pryſon and than ſayd ſome that he had deſerued to be hanged a ſome ſayde that it was done for the nonſe to deſeyne the wyne drower and that was but well done For be ſhulde haue ſene therto before for he ſayth dayly that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde begyle hym. but they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loued nat howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas ſayde that he was a thefe &amp; that he ſhulde be hanged and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was Howleglas browght before the Iuges and they gaue ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence that he ſhulde be hanged and on the morowe was he browght vnto the galowes for to be hanged for they that loued hym nat wolde fayne haue ſene iuſteyſe done on hym and there were gathered many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cowne to ſe Howleglas ſuffer dethe / but the lordes of Iubeke were ſoryefor hym for ſome went that he culde ſocery or wytchecrafre
<pb facs="tcp:18451:3"/>that he therwith ſimlde be delyuered and as he was led towarde the galowſe he lay all ſtyll as thowght he had bene all deed and when he cam under the galowes than deſyred he to ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lordes &amp; when the lordes were cum he fell u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his knes and prayed them that they wolde graunte hym a boue and the lordes ſayde that ſhulde be his lyfe that he wolde aſke. And than ſayde How leglas it ſhall not be my lyfe not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney nor it ſhulde nat coſte them one pennye of coſte And all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes of Iubeke went to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde of the galowes and toke acounſayll &amp; they repeted his wordes and than agreed to graunt hym his peryeyon &amp; cam to hym and bad hym aſke whatſoeuer he wolde ſaue thoſe wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were a boue reherſed. And than thanked howle glas the lordes and ſayd I pray you that euery oon of you wyll gyue me your handes thereon &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all to gyther gaue hym they: ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſo that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes had grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted hym both he w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worde and hande Than ſayd Howleglas to the lordes by cauſe I howe that ye be ſo faythefull of your wordes I ſhall ſhowe to you my bone and than he ſayd this is my bone that euery lorde of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beke to cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; kyſſe my ats when that I am han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon the galowes by the ſpace of .iij. dayes longe with his mowth in the mornynge faſtyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and the Gorowghe mayſter fyrſte and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18451:3"/>lordes after in order Than anſwered the lordes to Howleglas and ſayd that that was a vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly bone for to be aſked And then ſayd howle glas to the lordes of Iubeke I knowe the coun ſeyll of Iubeke ſo ſure of theyr ꝓmyſe that they wolde holde that they haue ꝓmyſed bothe with hande &amp; mowthe Then wentethe lordes ayene to counſayll and than ſayde the oon to the other this thynge that he aſkes of vs it is vnlaufully aſked for it were a great ſhame for vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be the greatteſte lordes of the towne ſhulde cum and kys his ars better it were for vs to gyue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his pardone &amp; let hym goo his waye for it is but aſmall faure that he hath done than agreed all the lordes and ſayde that it was beſte for to do / than called the lordes the Sergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and bad theym that they ſhulde vnbynde Howleglas &amp; let hym go at large for they all had gyuen hym his ꝑdon &amp; than dyd they vnloſe Howleglas &amp; when Howleglas was at large he thanked the lordes and than departed he fro Iubeke &amp; was delyuered and neuer cam there after.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas becam a maker of ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles and howe he culde fynde no worke in no la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de whereſoeuer he cam.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18451:4"/>
               <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on a tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seniatours of Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> great dyſcorde amonge them ſelfe whiche of all the lordes ſhuld be Emperoure And at the laſte was the Erle of Supplem browgh kyngs of Romanes and emperoure of Rome but the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re were many other that loked for it So when he was made he laye. vi. wekes longe before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> towne of Frankeforde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bydynge there for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other lordes to tourment where was a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany aſſembled And this herynge. Howleglas thowght in his mynde to goo thyder and ſo he and for there he thowght to get ſome gyfre and it were no more but the emperours ſyluer har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nepſe And as Howleglas paſſed be frankeford he met with the Byſſhop of Taer and by cauſe that he was clothed auenturelye he aſked hym what he was and Howleglas anſwered I am a ſpectacle maker cum out of Grabant and I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fynde no worke than ſayde the byſſhop m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke that youre crafte ſhulde be better dayly for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people the longer the ſyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe ſyght they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue therfore your crafte ſhulde be better dayly / &amp; than ſayd Howleglas to the byſſhop my lorde ye ſay trewthe but there is oon thynge that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth our crafte and if that ye wyll nat take no deſpleaſure I ſhall ſhowe it to you / and than the byſſhop bad hym ſay what he wolde &amp; than ſayde he this dell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wyes our crafte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re
<pb facs="tcp:18451:4"/>Than ſayd the merchaunte all angerly god d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue it vnder nethe the galowſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> / and as he was a lytell ferther he ſpyed a Galowes &amp; thyder dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued he the wagen vnder nethe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> galowes / and when it was vnder nethe he made the wagen to ſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vntyed the horſe Than ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the merchan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hat wyll ye nowe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Howleglas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ary here all nyght for ye b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dreue vnder the galowes Than when theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> galowſe then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but the merchaunt was angery and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dreue fourth ryght and neuer ſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſayde Howleglas he wolde than pulled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a pynne that is in the wagen that he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the horſe and droue the horſe fourthe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> folke ſtandyng ſtyll vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ynge this lep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> with hym and runne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> at the ſaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they ouer toke hym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te dreme his ſwerde and wolde haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hym but the pryſte wolde nat ſuffer hym / &amp; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made he faſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſe a geyne &amp; he than dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> out the iorney And whan the marchaunt was come home his wyfe aſked howe he fared and howe he lyked his man he anſwered ſo ſo than he called Howleglas and bad hym tary there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nyght and eate his belly full &amp; in the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nynge departe fro thenſe for he ſayde that he was but
<pb facs="tcp:18451:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>a begyler and a deſeyuer where ſo euer he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Than ſayde Howleglas good mayſter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall I doo and than a roſe Howleglas erly in the mor nynge and as he was vp the merchaunte ſayd eate and drynke your bellye full &amp; ryd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howſe of you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I fynde ye nathere when that I come ageyne for I muſte goo to chyrche for &amp; I fynde you here I ſhall bete you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhall beſhyte your breche And than hylde Howleglas his peace &amp; ſpake neuer a worde to hym and when that the merchaunce was at chyrche than began he for to ryd all the howſeholde ſtuffe out of the howſe and bare it into the ſtrete then worde cam to his mayſter to the chyrche that all his howſeholde ſtuffe ſtode in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrete Than cam y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te home &amp; ſawe that it was Howleglas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne out all his ſtuffe and aſked hym why he dyd ſo and Howleglas ſayd I do as ye bad me for ye bad me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhulde ryd your howſe and ſo I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of all your ſtuffe that ye haue / than ſayd the merchaunte to Howleglas departe fro henſe &amp; cum no more here with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delues name for here is no body that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes the for thy laboure and than departed Howleglas his way and ſo was the merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ſayne to cary in his gere ageyne that Howleglas had borne out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas was byd for a geſte.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18451:5"/>
               <p>IN Iune<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> borowgh dwelled a flewte maker that knewe well lande roners and knewe alſo muche decepte And on a tyme cam he to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ynne where Howleglas was and bad hym to mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owe at none cumere with me than than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Howleglas hym and ſayd that he wolde &amp; than departed the flewte maker home and on the morowe at none went Howleglas to the py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe makers howſe and when he cam there he fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de all the dores ſhyt and than walked he rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a boute the howſe tyll none was paſte and then knewe he well that he was deſeyued and retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned home a gayne and on the mornynge as he walked in the marker he ſpyed the pype maker and than went he to hym and thanked hym for his dyner and ſayde when ye byd a body ſhytte ye all youre dores / and the pype maker ſayde I bad you cum eate but you culde nat cum in fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I had ſhyt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dores and than he lawhed and ſayd goo to my howſe a fore &amp; I ſhall cum after to dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner for ye ſhall fynde there both roſte and ſodde and than departed Howleglas to the pype ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker howſe there he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de altrewe as the pype maker tolde hym and than ſayde he to the pype makers wyfe that ſhe ſhulde goo as faſte as ſhe culde to hyr huſhande and ſayde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had a gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at ſturgyn gyuen hym and ſayd that he wolde turne the ſpytte tyll that ſhe tam home a gayn
<pb facs="tcp:18451:6"/>the woman ſayd good Howleglas kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howſe tyll that I come a yeen and lette no body in than departed the woman with hyr mayde towarde hyr huſband as faſte as ſhe culde and met with hym by the way and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſawe hyr he aſked hyr wether ſhe wente ſo faſte and ſhe ſayd to hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe hym for ſhe ſayde that Howleglas had tolde to hir that ye had a ſturgen gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you and ſayde that ye bad that we ſhulde cum &amp; helpe you for it was ſo great that ye were nat able to bere it / than was the man angery and ſayd knowe ye nat well that Howleglas is ſuche a mocker and a deſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er than wente he home with his wyfe and when he cam home he knocked at the dore and Howleglas ſayde let be youre knockynge for the hooſte hathe charged me that I ſhall nat let no geſte in tyll dyner be done for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſayd that ſhe wolde be here than ſayd he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is trewth but ſhe ment nat ſo &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went he to his naygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and tared there to Howleglas had dyned and when that Howleglas had dyned and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de good there than opened he the dore and than the pypemaker cam in with all his folke And whan he was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in he ſayde to Howleglas that it was no honeſte for a geſte to ſhyt his hooſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe out of the dores and in this maner ſerued he his Hooſte and the hooſtayſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18451:6"/>with a good wyll and than toke Howleglas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhowne &amp; put in the lyttell ſhowne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſhowne and ſowed them bothe to gyther as his mayſter had byd hym and at the laſte that had ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed his mayſter and ſayd ye be a good ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ye do all thynge as men byd you / Than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tred Howleglas and ſayde / they that do as they be byd they be wordy to haue thanke than ſayde the mayſter ye do after my ſayinge and nat after my meanynge for I mente that fyrſte ye ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tide haue ſowed a lytell payre and after a great payer and the mayſter was haſtey &amp; toke hym other ledder and ſayde cut me all this led<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n laſte and the mayſter thought no more of the falſenes of Howleglas depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hamber and when he was come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> remne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bered he what he had ſapd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n wente he as faſte as he cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoppe whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as Howleglas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> three Howleglas had cut all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efte fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ayſter ſowe all his leder all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he Howleglas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>he leſee fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han ſayd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tye had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18451:7"/>the mayſter ſayde I had the cutte the one with the other and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwered Howleglas ye bad me cut all vpon on laſte than anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhowe maker if that I ſhulde kepe you longe you wol make me ſo pore that I muſte nedes goo a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge but nowe gyue me moneye for myled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that thou haſte marred me and departe fro henſe Than anſwered Howleglas to the ſhowe maker the hyde of a bull wyll make two hydes and with thoſe wordes aroſe he &amp; ſayde in this howſe haue I bene / but I wyll nat come here agayne and ſo departed he fro thenſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas ſolde courdes for fat.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Howleglas had deſtroyed muche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſhowemakers wherfore the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s uery ſory and that herynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ned ageyne to the towne and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r and tolde hym that he had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lde his mayſter that he ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e for to reſtore hym parte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d done to hym before in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhowemaker ſayde if it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me haue it before a nother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Howleglas with a good wyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tud then went Howleglas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and made hym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yll .xij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>relles
<pb facs="tcp:18451:7"/>with towedes for a lytell money and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toke he a lyttell talowe and put in the barelles .iiij. ynches thycke as thowghe it had bene all togyther grece and cloſed it ſo cloſe that it ſhulde not ſtynke for it was in the wynter when there was a great froſte that the durte was faſte fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to the barell and the other .vi. barelles he fyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led with other talowe or fat more thycker than the other .vi. were for they were the example of his merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſe And when that he had dreſſed all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> barelles he ſence for his mayſter the ſhowe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maker and aſked hym if that he wolde cum ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merchaundyſe and he ſayd he wolde / than with in a whyle cam y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhowemaker to Howleglas and when he was come there Howleglas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſte Barelles to be broken vp whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cordeenr ſawe the Barelles they lycked hym very well and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Howleglas aſked hym howethe Barelles pleaſed hym &amp; he anſwered very well and than aſked he the pryce and than anſwered Howleglas ye ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue me no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re than .xxiiij. guyld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> .xij. in ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de &amp; the other xij. at the yeres ende And than was the ſhowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker content and thowght no decente &amp; gaue to hym the .xij. gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in hande and he reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the money and departed &amp; was glad and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cordener was glad of the bargayne &amp; thowght that the forſayde harme that he had done hym
<pb facs="tcp:18451:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhulde be reſtored / and than he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>red manye fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes to melte the talowe and browght one ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rell by the fyer and when the durte began for to wexe whore than began it to ſmell than ſayde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Iwene ſome of vs hath beſhytyn theyr breche and than cam the mayſter and bad theym make clene theyr ſhowne for one of you hath trode in a courde and they loked all a bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te but they founde nothynge. And than ſhulde they haue put one of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> barelles in the cauderne than ſawe they well that it was the barell that ſtanke for it was full of turdes / And chan they lefte theyr worke &amp; went for to ſeke Howleglas but he was gone and ſo the ſhowemaker muſte ſuffer the laſte loſſe with the fyeſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas ſerued a Tayler.</head>
               <p>ON a tyme ſerued Howleglas a tayler and the tayler aſked hym if that he culde ſowe well and cloſe that no man cauſe the ſeme / and than ſayde Howleglas yea than went Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas &amp; ſowed vnder a barell than ſayd his may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter what doeſt thou nowe this is a meruelowſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſowynge / than anſwered Howleglas I ſowe ſo cloche that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe as ye bad me nor I my ſelfe ſe nat Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwered his mayſter good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt I ment nat ſo but ſome that euery man
<pb facs="tcp:18451:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſe &amp; he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d he wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde nyght the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad laboured ſo ſore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t he muſte nedes ſlepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſte he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Howleglas a huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gowne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bad hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a wolfe &amp; make it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and than ſayd How<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> I ſhall do than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he to bed than cut Howleglas the huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s man gowne and made therof a wolfe with hed and fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e And when that he had ſowed it to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther than ſet he it vpon the table with ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Than in the mornynge aroſe his mayſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cam downe and when he ſawe the wolfe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vpon the table he was a frayde &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hym what he had done / And he ſayde ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> I haue made a wolfe as ye bad me / than ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the maſter ment that ye ſhulde haue made vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ruſſet gowne for a huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des man gowne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led here a wolfe Than anſwered Howleglas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that I had knowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before I wolde haue done ſo for I had leuer haue made a gowne thanne a wolfe / and than at the laſte was the mayſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence And within. iiij. dayes after watched the mayſter ſo muche he muſte nedes goo ſlepe and there was a cote reddye made but it lacked the ſleues than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter toke the cote &amp; the ſleues and gaue theym to Howleglas and bad hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhulde caſte on the ſleues and he ſayd he wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de than went his mayſter to bed and than toke Howleglas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cote &amp; honge it on a balke &amp; ſet on
<pb facs="tcp:18451:9"/>euery ſyde a candell and ſtode vp and caſte the ſleues at the Cote all the nyght longe and than a roſe the the tayler and that ſpyed Howleglas and caſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſleues more faſter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he dyd before at the cote / and that aſſpyed the tayler and ſayd what folyſſhe toche is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you do there And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> anſwered Howleglas very angerly this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> folyſſhe toche for I haue ſtande all the nyght he recaſtynge the ſleues at the cote and they woll nat byde thereon and nowe I ſe it is but loſte la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure / Than ſayde the mayſter to Howleglas it is my faute for I wente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wolde haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande me better for I ment that you ſhulde haue ſowed on the ſleues to the cote Than ſayd Howleglas to his mayſter the deuyll take you for if ye had ſayd ſo to me before I myght haue ſowed on the ſleues and haue gonne ſlepte but nowe mayſter goo you and ſowe all the day lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and I wyll go ſlepe / And than anſwered the tayler haue I hyred you to ſlepe / &amp; thus began they to chyde &amp; as they were thus chydyng the tayler bad hym pay for his ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delles that he had by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned that nyght and than Howleglas ſpake neuer a worde more but toke al his clothes and went his waye and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am no more there.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:18451:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
